<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="//waingram.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="//waingram.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2024-12-11T22:37:06+00:00</updated><id>//waingram.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">William A. Ingram</title><subtitle>William A. Ingram is an academic leader and researcher who uses AI to structure and interpret scholarly data, advancing discovery, synthesis, accessibility, reproducibility, and transparency in open science.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Small, Locally-Hosted LLMs for Sustainable Development Goal Classification</title><link href="//waingram.github.io/blog/ieee-poster-sdg/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Small, Locally-Hosted LLMs for Sustainable Development Goal Classification" /><published>2024-12-05T17:36:48+00:00</published><updated>2024-12-05T17:36:48+00:00</updated><id>//waingram.github.io/blog/ieee-poster-sdg</id><content type="html" xml:base="//waingram.github.io/blog/ieee-poster-sdg/"><![CDATA[<p>We are excited to announce that <strong>“Agentic AI for Improving Precision in Identifying Contributions to Sustainable Development Goals”</strong> has been accepted as a poster at the 2024 IEEE International Conference on Big Data (<strong>IEEE BigData 2024</strong>), which will take place from <strong>December 15–18, 2024</strong>, in Washington, DC. <a href="http://bigdataieee.org/BigData2024/">Learn more about the conference</a>.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="about-the-study"><strong>About the Study</strong></h2>

<p>Accurately assessing research contributions to the United Nations’ Sustainable Development Goals (SDGs) is a growing priority for academic institutions. Traditional methods, which rely heavily on keyword-based Boolean search queries, often conflate incidental keyword matches with genuine contributions to SDG targets, leading to reduced precision in bibliometric analyses.</p>

<p>Our study proposes a novel approach: leveraging <strong>small, locally-hosted Large Language Models (LLMs)</strong> as evaluation agents to address the limitations of keyword-based retrieval. Using a dataset of 340,000 abstracts retrieved via SDG-specific keyword queries, we demonstrated how these models can distinguish between semantically relevant contributions to SDG targets and incidental mentions.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="key-highlights"><strong>Key Highlights</strong></h2>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Novel Application</strong>: We evaluated three small, locally-hosted LLMs—<strong>Mistral-7B</strong>, <strong>Phi-3.5-mini</strong>, and <strong>Llama-3.2</strong>—for their ability to classify SDG-related research contributions with greater precision than traditional methods.</li>
  <li><strong>Improved Precision</strong>: These models leverage their semantic understanding to move beyond surface-level keyword matching, addressing key limitations in traditional SDG classification workflows.</li>
  <li><strong>Scalability</strong>: By running these LLMs locally, the approach offers a cost-efficient and scalable framework for institutions to align research with SDG goals.</li>
</ul>

<hr />

<h2 id="why-it-matters"><strong>Why It Matters</strong></h2>

<p>This work represents a step forward in SDG-related research evaluation, providing a more nuanced and precise approach to classifying scholarly contributions. The findings have broader implications for institutional benchmarking, funding strategies, and semantic search applications.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="future-directions"><strong>Future Directions</strong></h2>

<p>Our research paves the way for:</p>
<ol>
  <li>Developing <strong>multi-agent frameworks</strong> that combine multiple models to refine classification further.</li>
  <li>Applying these techniques in <strong>semantic search systems</strong> to enable more effective discovery of SDG-relevant research.</li>
</ol>

<hr />

<h2 id="read-the-full-preprint"><strong>Read the Full Preprint</strong></h2>

<p>The full preprint of our work is available on <strong>arXiv</strong>: <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.17598">https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.17598</a>.</p>

<p>We look forward to presenting this work at <strong>IEEE BigData 2024</strong> and engaging with the community on the potential of LLMs in advancing SDG-related research.</p>

<hr />]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="AI," /><category term="SDGs," /><category term="IEEE," /><category term="BigData," /><category term="Poster" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[We are excited to announce that “Agentic AI for Improving Precision in Identifying Contributions to Sustainable Development Goals” has been accepted as a poster at the 2024 IEEE International Conference on Big Data (IEEE BigData 2024), which will take place from December 15–18, 2024, in Washington, DC. Learn more about the conference.]]></summary></entry></feed>